Nelson E. Díaz-Díaz

☎+57-314-236-7334 ⊠nelson.diaz@saber.uis.edu.co LP 255

Bucaramanga, Colombia, Cra 27 calle 9, 680002

Bio: Received the B. Sc. and M. Sc. degrees in Computer Science from the Universidad Industrial de Santander, Colombia, in 2012 and 2015, respectively, and Ph. D. degrees in Electronic Engineering from the Universidad Industrial de Santander, Bucaramanga, Colombia in 2020, sponsored by a 727 Colciencias scholarship. Currently, he holds a Postdoctoral position with the Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso (PUCV), Santiago, Chile, under the supervision of Prof. Esteban Vera. His research interests include high-dimensional signal processing, sparse image representation, adaptive sensing, compressive video, and spectral image classification. **WebPage:** https://nelson10.github.io/

SKILLS

- Languages: Spanish (Native), English (B2), French (B2)
- Programming: Python (NumPy, SciPy, Matplotlib), MATLAB
- Document Creation: Office tools, LATEX

PROFESSIONAL EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy in Engineering: emphasis in electronic

2016-2020

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering

Universidad Industrial de Santander, Bucaramanga, Santander, Colombia

GPA: 4.55/5.00

Advisor: PhD. Henry Arguello

Doctoral thesis: "Coded Aperture Design for Adaptive Compressive Spectral Imaging"

Master of Science in Computer Science

2013-2015

Department of Computer Science

Universidad Industrial de Santander, Bucaramanga, Colombia.

GPA: 4.72/5.00

Advisor: Ph.D. Henry Arguello.

Master thesis: "High-dynamic range compressive spectral imaging by adaptive filtering"

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science

2006-2012

Department of Computer Science

Universidad Industrial de Santander, Bucaramanga, Colombia.

GPA: 3.88/5.00

Advisor: Ph.D. Lola Xiomara.

Graduate project:: "Immune algorithm to solve job shop scheduling".

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Research Associate - School of Electrical Engineering

August 2020 - Present

Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaiso, Chile

Valparaiso, Chile

Assistant Professor Data Structures, Fundamentals of programming, February 2020 - July 2020 Technology of the Information and Communication TIC

Department of Computer Science

Universidad de Investigación y Desarrollo, Bucaramanga, Colombia

Fall-winter 2018-2019
2016-2017
Summer 2015
2013-Present
2011-2012
March 10th, 2020
2016 - 2019 y
2012 - 2013
2019 - Present
2019 - Present
2021 - Present

Universidad Industrial de Santander, Colombia

2013 - Present

Collaboration with Dr. Henry Arguello

Project: Adaptive grayscale coded aperture design

Other activities: Joint development of grants and application to the Colombian Institute

of Development of Science and Technology - Colciencias

JOURNAL PAPERS

- 1. Esteban Vera, Felipe Guzmán, and Nelson Díaz. Shuffled rolling shutter for snapshot temporal imaging. *Opt. Express*, 30(2):887–901, Jan 2022
- Nelson Diaz, Omar Gallo, Jhon Caceres, and Hernan Porras. Real-time ground filtering algorithm
 of cloud points acquired using terrestrial laser scanner (tls). *International Journal of Applied Earth
 Observation and Geoinformation*, 105:102629, 2021
- 3. N. Diaz, J. M. Ramirez, E. Vera, and H. Arguello. Adaptive classification via spatial contextual information in multisensor compressive spectral imaging. *IEEE Journal of Selected Topics in Applied Earth Observations and Remote Sensing*, 14:9254–9266, 2021
- 4. Nelson Diaz, Carlos Hinojosa, and Henry Arguello. Adaptive grayscale compressive spectral imaging using optimal blue noise coding patterns. *Optics & Laser Technology*, 117:147–157, September 2019
- 5. Nelson Diaz, Hoover Rueda, and Henry Arguello. Adaptive filter design via a gradient thresholding algorithm for compressive spectral imaging. *Applied Optics*, 57(17):4890–4900, June 2018
- Edson Flórez, Nelson Díaz, Wilfredo Gómez, Lola Bautista, and Darío Delgado. Evaluación de algoritmos bioinspirados para la solución del problema de planificación de trabajos. I+ D Revista de Investigaciones, 11(1):133–143, 2018
- Nelson Diaz, Hoover Rueda Chacon, and Henry Arguello Fuentes. High-dynamic range compressive spectral imaging by grayscale coded aperture adaptive filtering. *Ingeniería e Investigación*, 35(3):53– 60, 2015

CONFERENCE PAPERS

- 1. Felipe Guzmán, Nelson Díaz, and Esteban Vera. Improved compressive temporal imaging using a shuffled rolling shutter. In *OSA Optical Sensors and Sensing Congress 2021 (AIS, FTS, HISE, SEN-SORS, ES)*, page JTh6A.9. Optical Society of America, 2021
- 2. J. Bacca, N. Diaz, and H. Arguello. Compressive classification via deep learning using single-pixel measurements. In 2020 Data Compression Conference (DCC), pages 359–359, 2020
- 3. N. Diaz, C. Noriega-Wandurraga, A. Basarab, J.Y Tourneret, and H Arguello. Adaptive coded aperture design by motion estimation using convolutional sparse coding in compressive spectral video sensing. In 2019 IEEE 8th International Workshop on Computational Advances in Multi-Sensor Adaptive Processing (CAMSAP), Guadeloupe, France, pages 1–5, Dec 2019
- 4. N. Diaz, A. Basarab, J.Y. Tourneret, and H. Arguello. Cardiac motion estimation using convolutional sparse coding. In 2019 27th European Signal Processing Conference (EUSIPCO), Coruña, España, Sep 2019
- 5. M. Marquez, N. Diaz, J. Bacca, S. Pertuz, and H. Arguello. Compressive light field spectral imaging in a single-sensor device by using coded apertures. In *Imaging and Applied Optics 2017 (3D, AIO, COSI, IS, MATH, pcAOP)*, page CTh1B.5. Optical Society of America, 2017

- N. Diaz, J. Bacca, and H. Arguello. Gradient thresholding algorithm for adaptive colored coded aperture design in compressive spectral imaging. In *Imaging and Applied Optics 2017 (3D, AIO, COSI, IS, MATH, pcAOP), San Francisco, California*, page JTu5A.4. Optical Society of America, 2017
- Nelson Diaz, Hoover Rueda, and Henry Arguello. Adaptive uniform grayscale coded aperture design
 for high dynamic range compressive spectral imaging. In *Hyperspectral Imaging Sensors: Innova-*tive Applications and Sensor Standards, Baltimore, USA, volume 9860, page 98600A. International
 Society for Optics and Photonics, 2016
- 8. N. Diaz, H. Rueda, and H. Arguello. High-dynamic range compressive spectral imaging by adaptive filtering. In 2015 3rd International Workshop on Compressed Sensing Theory and its Applications to Radar, Sonar and Remote Sensing (CoSeRa), pages 89–93, June 2015

MEMBERSHIPS

- IEEE Signal Processing Society, Member
- Optica (Formerly Optical Society of America), Member